<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[No Such Thing as Two]]></title>
  <link href="http://nwallace.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://nwallace.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-04-03T17:20:13-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://nwallace.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Nathan Wallace]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[nathan@nosuchthingastwo.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Getting Started with Ruby]]></title>
    <link href="http://nwallace.github.io/blog/2014/04/03/getting-started-with-ruby/"/>
    <updated>2014-04-03T04:26:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://nwallace.github.io/blog/2014/04/03/getting-started-with-ruby</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I&#39;m self-taught in Ruby. I owe a huge debt to the incredible Ruby community for
being able to do that. Most of the developers I know do Java or C++ (since
that&#39;s what they taught in college), and when I told them I was looking for a
Ruby job a lot of them were curious about the appeal. I have been trying to
<del>save</del> convert them, and I wanted to jot down my path to
<del>salvation</del> learn Ruby so others could do the same.</p>

<h2>First steps</h2>

<h3>Get a handle on the language</h3>

<p>There are tons of awesome resources on the web for learning Ruby, but my
favorite for anyone just starting out is
<a href="http://www.codecademy.com/tracks/ruby">Codecademy</a>. Codecademy has tracks for a
lot more than just Ruby, and I&#39;ve had a great experience with all of the ones
I&#39;ve tried. They&#39;re perfect for people who have never programmed Ruby before,
and I think they would be great for people who have never programmed at all
before. The tracks get more and more advanced as you go along, so there are
resources here for people who may have played around with Ruby in the past as
well, but don&#39;t know the language very well.</p>

<h3>Reach enlightenment</h3>

<p>After getting a feel for the syntax and basic usage of the language, I moved
onto the <a href="http://rubykoans.com/">Ruby Koans</a>. The Koans are a special kind of
experience. They walk you through different features of the language like your
own personal Mr. Miyagi. They start to engrain the idea of test-driven
development while going in-depth on language constructs and the standard
library.</p>

<h3>Hop on the Rails</h3>

<p>Let&#39;s be real &#8211; people learn Ruby so they can write Rails apps. Yes, Ruby is an
awesome language in its own right, but that&#39;s not why most people pick it up.
The absolute best tutorial for a beginner to learn Rails is the one by Michael
Hartl. You can read his book online for free at
<a href="http://ruby.railstutorial.org/">ruby.railstutorial.org</a>. The source is on
Github for easy reference if you make a mistake, and there are lots of <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/tagged/railstutorial.org">Stack
Overflow</a> answers
to help you along as well. Hartl&#39;s tutorial walks you through building a Twitter
clone, teaching you Rails, TDD, Twitter Bootstrap, and Heroku along the way. It
was invaluable for me as a way to really sink your teeth into a real Rails app.</p>

<h3>Bring it home</h3>

<p>After that, you <em>have</em> to start your own project. Tutorials are great, but they
hold your hand the whole way &#8211; they don&#39;t force you answer any of your own
questions or come up with your own ideas. If you don&#39;t already have a project
idea in mind, do what inspired me: find a problem where someone is using an
Excel spreadsheet and turn it into a web app. My aunt is a chef, and she was
using Excel to track inventory and expenses, so I turned it into a Rails app.
The most important thing about the project is that it needs to be something to
keep you motivated. Motivation is the largest hurdle in learning a new language
or framework, so you need to be personally invested in solving your problem.</p>

<p>It took me about 8 months of my free time to get to a place where I really felt
comfortable in Ruby and with Rails, so don&#39;t get discouraged if it takes awhile.
At the end of the day, Ruby is about <strong>joy</strong>. It&#39;s optimized for you, the
developer. So have fun with it, and try to improve just a little everyday.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[I have a blog!]]></title>
    <link href="http://nwallace.github.io/blog/2014/03/21/i-have-a-blog/"/>
    <updated>2014-03-21T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://nwallace.github.io/blog/2014/03/21/i-have-a-blog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Thanks for visiting my blog! This blog is under construction right now, but I will have my first post out soon. :)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
